<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Victory Formation</title>
 <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/"/>
 <updated>2014-02-15T15:57:03-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://lyzidiamond.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Victory Formation</name>
 </author>
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>What even is TileMill?</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/wtf-tilemill"/>
   <updated>2014-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/wtf-tilemill</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The other day, my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/allafarce&quot;&gt;Dave&lt;/a&gt; asked me, &amp;ldquo;Okay. So what does &lt;a href=&quot;http://tilemill.com&quot;&gt;TileMill&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;actually do&lt;/strong&gt;?&amp;rdquo; This was my response (with the curse words edited out, and a few links thrown in). I was told it&amp;rsquo;d be useful to people. Enjoy!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Tue, Jan 28, 2014 at 3:43 PM, &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com&quot;&gt;Lyzi Diamond&lt;/a&gt; wrote:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TileMill allows you to load in &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GIS_file_formats#Vector_formats&quot;&gt;vector&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GIS_file_formats#Raster_formats&quot;&gt;raster&lt;/a&gt; data, style it using a language called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/&quot;&gt;CartoCSS&lt;/a&gt; (often abbreviated &amp;ldquo;carto&amp;rdquo;), and export raster &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Tiles&quot;&gt;map tiles&lt;/a&gt;. Map tiles can be exported as PNG, SVG, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/developers/mbtiles/&quot;&gt;MBTiles&lt;/a&gt;, which is &lt;a href=&quot;http://mapbox.com&quot;&gt;Mapbox&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s format. TileMill also allows you to add feature layers on top of your tiles, which are vector layers that have some sort of interactivity (tooltips, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TileMill only allows you to have one interactivity/feature layer at a time. Typically the interaction involves tooltips. That&amp;rsquo;s the basic interactivity functionality built in to TileMill (you can do more stuff in &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com&quot;&gt;Leaflet&lt;/a&gt;, as I&amp;rsquo;m sure you know). Because you&amp;rsquo;re loading in (mostly) vector layers that have a lot of data associated with them (attributes/properties/columns in a database table/whatever else you want to call it), you can pull from that data to make individualized tooltips without hardcoding them. There&amp;rsquo;s more info on how to do that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/crashcourse/tooltips/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Styling vector layers is also a pretty cool thing that can pull from attribute information &amp;ndash; if you wanted to make &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.gis.com/wiki/index.php/Graduated_Symbols&quot;&gt;graduated symbols&lt;/a&gt; based on the values of some attribute, you can do that within CartoCSS. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of functionality there. You can read more about styling in TileMill &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/tilemill/docs/manual/carto/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bread and butter of TileMill is obviously tiles. It seems really trivial, right? Why can&amp;rsquo;t I just draw some crap on some images and put those images in a map? There are a few reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A map tile is a very specific thing. Map tiles are 256x256 pixel images that are placed side by side inside of a web map to give the illusion of one very large, seamless image. Maps have specific zoom levels that are explicitly defined, from zoom level 0 through zoom level 20. Zoom level 0 is one tile for the whole world. It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zoom0.png&quot; alt=&quot;Zoom Level 0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zoom level 1 is four tiles for the whole world, in a 2x2 grid. Zoom level 2 is 16 tiles for the whole world, in a 4x4 grid. You see where this is going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zoom levels are the same across all tilesets. Zoom level 0 is always going to be one tile for the world, 1 will be four tiles, etc. You can imagine that the whole world at zoom level 20 gets pretty unwieldy. It&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt; of data. When you&amp;rsquo;re zoomed way in and panning around a map, only the tiles that are being viewed are rendered, and then cached. It&amp;rsquo;s actually quite efficient and does create the illusion of a seamless image, because you are only ever rendering a subset of the tiles, which doesn&amp;rsquo;t take very long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The URL for the tile above is http://a.tiles.mapbox.com/v3/lyzidiamond.map-ietb6srb/0/0/0.png. The first part is obviously the server. The last three numbers, as I&amp;rsquo;m sure you&amp;rsquo;ve figured out, delineate the zoom level and the x/y location of that particular tile in the grid. Zoom 0 is a pretty bad example of this. Let&amp;rsquo;s go to zoom 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zoom-1-1-0.png&quot; alt=&quot;Zoom Level 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the tile in the first row in the second column of the zoom level 1 2x2 grid. Its URL is http://a.tiles.mapbox.com/v3/lyzidiamond.map-ietb6srb/1/1/0.png. You can see that at the end of the URL, it shows us that we&amp;rsquo;re looking at a tile from zoom level 1 in the 1, 0 part of the grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tilegrid.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tile Grid&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two more, way zoomed in, just for fun:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zoom-12-1009-1878.png&quot; alt=&quot;Zoom Level 12&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;URL: http://a.tiles.mapbox.com/v3/lyzidiamond.map-ietb6srb/12/1009/1878.png&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/zoom-12-1009-1879.png&quot; alt=&quot;Zoom Level 12&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;URL: http://a.tiles.mapbox.com/v3/lyzidiamond.map-ietb6srb/12/1009/1879.png, or the tile right below the previous one. Get it? Pretty cool, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you&amp;rsquo;ve now deduced that there&amp;rsquo;s a pretty rigorous file structure that is required to manage all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tile-files.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tile File Structure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that in this image, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have every zoom level, or even the entirety of the grid. TileMill will ask you for a) a geographic area and b) the number of zoom levels you want before you export. If you&amp;rsquo;re trying to do something too epically large, or with a ton of layers that are going to be annoying/resource-consuming to render down, it&amp;rsquo;ll give you a nice little warning, along the lines of &amp;ldquo;HEY JERKFACE WE DON&amp;rsquo;T WANNA DO THAT FIX YR STUFF.&amp;rdquo; But nicer. Then they export your tiles into this file structure, and indeed host them as well. If they&amp;rsquo;re hosting a ton of your crap or you&amp;rsquo;re getting a ton of views, they ask you to pay them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Mostly, these are PNGs. Mapbox likes its MBTiles format for a bunch of reasons, one of which is that some tiles [particularly in the middle of water bodies] are always going to look the same, at every zoom level and in any location. You can read them loving on it more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/developers/mbtiles/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Editor&amp;rsquo;s note: the original version of the following paragraph was incorrect, so I&amp;rsquo;ve included an updated version here.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, on to &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Vector_tiles&quot;&gt;vector tiles&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/blog/vector-tiles/&quot;&gt;Vector tiles&lt;/a&gt; use data structure magic (&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protocol_Buffers&quot;&gt;protocol buffers&lt;/a&gt;) to store all sorts of information you&amp;rsquo;d have in a geographic vector data layer and then renders it into images on the fly. This makes it really awesomely space-efficient; the entirety of &lt;a href=&quot;http://openstreetmap.org&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s data as vector tiles can fit on just about 60GB, &lt;a href=&quot;https://vine.co/v/b0DvTPnpPtw&quot;&gt;small enough to fit on a thumb drive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vector tiles are going to be a part of TileMill2 when it&amp;rsquo;s released, which will also come pre-loaded with the whole world in OSM vectors. Seriously. Mapbox is maybe the coolest company ever of ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure I missed some stuff. Let me know if you have any other questions. Sorry I wrote an essay, but that&amp;rsquo;s kind of what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Geographic Awakening</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/geographic-awakening"/>
   <updated>2013-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/geographic-awakening</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://education.nationalgeographic.com/media/photos/000/344/custom/34437_610x343.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Geography Awareness Week&quot; /&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week is &lt;a href=&quot;http://geographyawarenessweek.org&quot;&gt;Geography Awareness Week&lt;/a&gt;, a whole week dedicated to the study and understanding of our world through a geographic lens. It was established by presidential proclamation in 1987 (pop quiz: who was president in 1987?) in order to promote geographic education in our classrooms and in our lives at large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the fact that we have to designate a specific week for the study of geography is a saddening fact. Geography just doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist explicitly in schools anymore, at any level. Yes, including universities. A large part of the problem is that there isn&amp;rsquo;t a clear understanding among the general population of what geography actually &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. When I tell people I was a geography major, they assume my program involved learning the names and locations of the world&amp;rsquo;s capital cities and hand drawing maps with colored pencils. Before I took my first geography class at the University of Oregon, I thought much the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the classes I was fortunate enough to take at UO was called Human Geographic Thought, a ten week walk through the history of geography, how it became a field of study, and contributions of major geographers over time. One of the textbooks for the class was &lt;em&gt;Modern Geographical Thought&lt;/em&gt; by Richard Peet, a text that traces the history of geography and juxtaposes it against sociological and philosophical changes and advancements over time, illustrating how geography really is an interdisciplinary science that affects more aspects of our daily lives than anyone actively considers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book&amp;rsquo;s introduction, Peet provides an excellent definition of the field of geography:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Geography is the study of relations between society and the natural environment. Geography looks at how society shapes, alters, and increasingly transforms the natural environment, creating humanized forms from stretches of pristine nature, and then sedimenting layers of socialization one within the other, one on top of the other, until a complex natural-social landscape results. Geography also looks at how nature conditions society, in some original sense of creating the people and raw materials which social forces &amp;ldquo;work up&amp;rdquo; into culture, and in an ongoing sense of placing limits and offering material potentials for social processes like economic development. The &amp;ldquo;relation&amp;rdquo; between society and nature is thus an entire system, a complex of interrelations. What was once a causal relationship mainly in one direction (the formation of humanity during natural evolution) becomes an equally causal interrelationship in the reverse direction (social evolution alters the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; environment). In this way, human activity continually remakes its natural context — nature comes to be socially constructed, in the sense both of social and economic forces remaking landscapes, and of the intervention of ideas and discourses. Understanding this system of relations requires that geographers be sophisticated natural and social scientists, find ways of combining the two, know the methods and be excited by the insights of both aspects of knowledge. Thus, the synthetic core of geography is a study of nature-society interrelations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geography is the study of people, place, and how they interact with each other, how they affect each other. It affects everyone and everything, by definition. It is part of so many fields of study, not usually in name, but always in practice. So let&amp;rsquo;s venture to make every week geography awareness week. Let&amp;rsquo;s consider our place in the world, how our actions affect that place and how that place affects our actions. Let&amp;rsquo;s teach and learn geography based on its true definition: not by memorizing state capitals, but understanding why the capital is where it is in the first place. Once we realize that geography really is all around us, we can make better decisions based on this new understanding of our world.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Open Source FTW!</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/open-source-ftw"/>
   <updated>2013-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/open-source-ftw</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For some time, I&amp;rsquo;ve been frustrated with the lack of social spaces for developers to work together on map-related projects here in Portland. There are &lt;a href=&quot;http://calagator.org&quot;&gt;language-specific meetups&lt;/a&gt;, and there are definitely people hacking on spatial projects at those, but it&amp;rsquo;s in the context of the programming language, not the field of geospatial tech. I have also long been fascinated with the pedagogical issues of teaching developers about geographic principles and geographers about computer programming. I began wondering: is there a place for a meetup like this in Portland?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point during this thought process, I discovered &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/maptimesf&quot;&gt;MaptimeSF&lt;/a&gt;, a weekly map hack night run by a few of the excellent folks over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://stamen.com&quot;&gt;Stamen&lt;/a&gt; in San Francsico. I heard that there were a couple similar groups popping up around the country, so I decided to get in contact about starting one in Portland. Thus was born &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/maptimepdx&quot;&gt;MaptimePDX&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;MaptimePDX is ON! Sunday 9/29, 1pm-4pm at Flux (&lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/aYGp0GPG3E&quot;&gt;http://t.co/aYGp0GPG3E&lt;/a&gt;), part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WhereCampPDX&quot;&gt;@WhereCampPDX&lt;/a&gt;. EXCITED! More info: &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/iLH0CmtXOd&quot;&gt;http://t.co/iLH0CmtXOd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; MaptimePDX (@MaptimePDX) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MaptimePDX/statuses/382250375849320448&quot;&gt;September 23, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This past weekend was &lt;a href=&quot;http://wherecamppdx.org&quot;&gt;WhereCampPDX&lt;/a&gt;, which seemed like the perfect time to hold the inaugural MaptimePDX event. In addition to hosting an open hack for anyone who was interested in joining us, I prepared a little exercise I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to write for a while. It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/lyzidiamond/learn-geojson&quot;&gt;Learn GeoJSON&lt;/a&gt;, and its goal is to teach about the principles and ideas of &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.org&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://geojson.org&quot;&gt;GeoJSON&lt;/a&gt; without having to lead beginners through dealing with (a) code and (b) the command line. You can view the slides I used for my presentation &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/learn-geojson/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who&amp;#39;s excited for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MaptimePDX&quot;&gt;@MaptimePDX&lt;/a&gt; today? I am! I&amp;#39;m also frantically finishing up the exercise we&amp;#39;re going to do :-P&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Lyzi Diamond (@lyzidiamond) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lyzidiamond/statuses/384381323470577665&quot;&gt;September 29, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is to use GitHub as a collaboration tool for building crowd-sourced geographic (GeoJSON) datasets with the help of the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://geojson.io&quot;&gt;geojson.io&lt;/a&gt;. Essentially, users fork the original (my) repo, open their desired geojson files using geojson.io (which gives them the option of clicking back and forth between a table-based format and GeoJSON format — hooray unintentional learning tools!), add some points visually, commit to their repo, and make a pull request back to the original repo. (Further information and more detailed instructions are available on the README in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/lyzidiamond/learn-geojson&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. I also intend on writing a blog post about it once it&amp;rsquo;s totally done, so look out for that.) It actually went pretty smoothly up to that point, which was awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I turned back to the projector to show an example of merging a pull request, seeing as I had about ten of them at that point, and lo and behold&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/lyzidiamond/lyzidiamond.github.com/master/images/mergeconflict.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every pull request had a merge conflict! I got super frustrated, asked the group to talk amongst themselves, and investigated a little bit. When I checked the diff, this is what I saw:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/lyzidiamond/lyzidiamond.github.com/master/images/diff.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every feature in the dataset was on the same line! JavaScript doesn&amp;rsquo;t care about line breaks, so this is definitely acceptable and is totally still valid GeoJSON, but makes it near impossible for use with this collaboration technique I was preaching. I didn&amp;rsquo;t even notice it beforehand, because it appears to be line broken in geojson.io:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/lyzidiamond/lyzidiamond.github.com/master/images/geojsonio.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A conundrum, to be certain. I thought to myself, &amp;ldquo;Ugh, I can&amp;rsquo;t believe I didn&amp;rsquo;t figure this out ahead of time. How could I screw this up so badly?&amp;rdquo; It wasn&amp;rsquo;t a pretty scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But fortunately, I was surrounded by a few of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/reidab&quot;&gt;great&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/pdxmele&quot;&gt;geo hackers&lt;/a&gt; I had been so eager to recruit to MaptimePDX. And they said, &amp;ldquo;You know, geojson.io is an open source project. We can just add some code to implement line breaks, make a pull request, and see if it gets merged!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So they did. And less than an hour later&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/lyzidiamond/lyzidiamond.github.com/master/images/merged.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was merged! Mele checked it afterwards, and it &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pdxmele/pdxpyconmap/commit/7890ee0924e987eda955c6218d95778026fd9384&quot;&gt;totally works&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/lyzidiamond/lyzidiamond.github.com/master/images/melecommit.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, save for having to resolve the conflicts with each of the commits made pre-prettifying, this exercise will work completely smoothly in the future. I can&amp;rsquo;t wait to present it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is a long story.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But everyone has one of these stories — stories that make them realize what&amp;rsquo;s been right in front of them the whole time. And this is mine: &lt;strong&gt;open source is the future.&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m hooked. I&amp;rsquo;m completely and totally hooked. I think Mele put it best:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lyzidiamond&quot;&gt;@lyzidiamond&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reidab&quot;&gt;@reidab&lt;/a&gt; open source FTW&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mele Sax-Barnett (@pdxmele) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pdxmele/statuses/384455625674989568&quot;&gt;September 29, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s contribute to all the things!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non sequiturs: Sometime soon I&amp;rsquo;ll write a more in-depth post discussing the &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/lyzidiamond/learn-geojson&quot;&gt;Learn GeoJSON&lt;/a&gt; exercise, how it works, what needs to be added to it, and how it may solve some of the pedagogical problems with getting geographers into tech. On a similar note, I hosted an unconference session at WhereCampPDX about geospatial pedagogy that yielded an interesting discussion. I&amp;rsquo;ll write about that here, too.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>External GeoJSON and Leaflet: The Other Way(s)</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/external-geojson-and-leaflet-the-other-way"/>
   <updated>2013-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/external-geojson-and-leaflet-the-other-way</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I will always be a student. In the wide world of geospatial technology, we are all going to be students forever. So when someone from Twitter tells me a better way to do something that seems intuitive and worthwhile, I have no problem sharing it with the world, even when it contradicts something I said before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m specifically talking about my last technical post, &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/osgeo-august-meeting/&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Adding GeoJSON to Leaflet with Link Relations&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. The technique I outlined totally worked, and people seem to be enjoying using it, but as is usual for these sorts of things, someone from Twitter offered another suggestion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vtcraghead&quot;&gt;@vtcraghead&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lyzidiamond&quot;&gt;@lyzidiamond&lt;/a&gt; How is this advantageous to: $.getJSON(&amp;quot;mydata.geojson&amp;quot;, function (data) {&amp;#10;markers.addData(data);&amp;#10;});&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Bryan McBride (@brymcbride) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/brymcbride/statuses/382535707798929408&quot;&gt;September 24, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I thought about this for a minute. Why &lt;em&gt;wasn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; I just passing my GeoJSON file directly into jQuery&amp;rsquo;s getJSON method? I thought I had tried it and it hadn&amp;rsquo;t worked. But then I tried it. And it &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/cupcakes_fail.html&quot;&gt;totally worked&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at this code, and compare it to the code I posted last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Passing JSON directly into getJSON method.&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;!doctype html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.css&quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;!--[if lte IE 8]&amp;gt;
     &amp;lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.ie.css&quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;![endif]--&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&amp;gt;
    body {
      padding: 0;
      margin: 0;
    }

    html, body, #cupcake-map {
      height: 100%;
    }

  &amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&quot;http://code.jquery.com/jquery-1.10.2.min.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div id=&quot;cupcake-map&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
  var cupcakeTiles = L.tileLayer(&#39;http://a.tiles.mapbox.com/v3/lyzidiamond.map-ietb6srb/{z}/{x}/{y}.png&#39;, {
    maxZoom: 18
  });

  $.getJSON(&quot;./cupcakes.json&quot;, function(data) {
    var geojson = L.geoJson(data, {
      onEachFeature: function (feature, layer) {
        layer.bindPopup(feature.properties.name);
      }
    });
    var map = L.map(&#39;cupcake-map&#39;).fitBounds(geojson.getBounds());
    cupcakeTiles.addTo(map);
    geojson.addTo(map);
  });
  &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main differences. First of all, the link relation in the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is gone. Second, the first argument to the jQuery getJSON method is different. Instead of using some additional jQuery code to identify the linked JSON and pull out the content, we just simply pass the JSON file &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; into the method. (The second argument remains the same, a callback function upon successful &amp;ldquo;getting&amp;rdquo; of JSON.) Everything else is the same. And as you &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/cupcakes_fail.html&quot;&gt;can see&lt;/a&gt;, it looks &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/cupcakes.html&quot;&gt;exactly the same&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;This is great! Should I just use this instead of link relations all the time?&lt;/h2&gt;




&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vtcraghead&quot;&gt;@vtcraghead&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lyzidiamond&quot;&gt;@lyzidiamond&lt;/a&gt; Might need to be proxied if cross-domain...&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Bryan McBride (@brymcbride) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/brymcbride/statuses/382541743947665408&quot;&gt;September 24, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No. This technique worked for me because my &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/cupcakes_fail.html&quot;&gt;cupcakes.html&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/cupcakes.json&quot;&gt;cupcakes.json&lt;/a&gt; files are in the same domain. If my files were in separate domains, I would have to create a proxy. (There is a nice example of a simple PHP proxy and an example its usage with jQuery&amp;rsquo;s getJSON method &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/bmcbride/6614373#file-proxy-php&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. According to Twitter, you can write these proxies in other languages too, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/billdollins/status/382561454500487168&quot;&gt;it can be annoying/time consuming&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proxy is required when using this method because of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Same_origin_policy_for_JavaScript&quot;&gt;same-origin policy&lt;/a&gt;, which affects browser-side programming languages. The policy sets restrictions on how scripts loaded from one origin can interact with resources from different origins in the interest of security (&amp;ldquo;origins&amp;rdquo; meaning &amp;ldquo;domains&amp;rdquo; in this case). Most methods and properties are not accessible when being requested from a different domain, so a proxy domain must be created to mimic a same-origin request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Oh. That sounds annoying. Is there another way?&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You bet. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CWMma&quot;&gt;Calvin Metcalf&lt;/a&gt; has created a nice little plugin for &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com&quot;&gt;Leaflet&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/calvinmetcalf/leaflet-ajax&quot;&gt;leaflet-ajax&lt;/a&gt; that allows you to make a request for JSON using Ajax and allows a request/response for JSONP, making it possible to pull JSON from another domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var geojsonLayer = new L.GeoJSON.AJAX(&quot;./cupcakes.json&quot;);
var geojsonLayer = new L.GeoJSON.AJAX(&quot;http:example.com/cupcakes.jsonp&quot;, {dataType:&quot;jsonp&quot;});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wait, wait, back up. AJAX? JSONP? What?&lt;/h2&gt;




&lt;h3&gt;Ajax&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/AJAX/Getting_Started&quot;&gt;Ajax&lt;/a&gt; stands for Asynchronous JavaScript and XML. It is a way for web applications to send data to and receive data from a server asynchronously, without disrupting the behavior of the page where the request was originated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, when we are loading our GeoJSON file onto the page, we are loading it from the server and displaying it in the browser, which means communication needs to occur from the server-side, or back end, to the client-side, or front end. This communication happens at different times, depending on when the data is requested. In the example above, we are requesting the data in the getJSON method. In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/osgeo-august-meeting/&quot;&gt;previous example&lt;/a&gt;, we were requesting the data in the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, so the request was being made before the getJSON method was called. With Calvin&amp;rsquo;s plugin, an Ajax request is being made when a variable is created for the geoJSON layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;JSONP&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://json-p.org/&quot;&gt;JSONP&lt;/a&gt; stands for &amp;ldquo;JSON with padding.&amp;rdquo; It exists primarily to thwart the previously mentioned &lt;em&gt;same-origin policy&lt;/em&gt; and uses one of the allowed cross-domain mechanisms to get JSON from a different domain. I am not going to go into how JSONP works here; for more information on its structure and history, click the link. (EXTRA CREDIT: There is another, more commonly used tool for allowing JavaScript requests to be made across browsers, caled &lt;a href=&quot;http://enable-cors.org/&quot;&gt;cross-origin resource sharing, or CORS&lt;/a&gt;. It isn&amp;rsquo;t yet a standard for this type of practice, however, because Internet Explorer has yet to implement it, making it a poor cross-&lt;em&gt;browser&lt;/em&gt; solution.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;So how would that work, then?&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As always, let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at the code (live example &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/cupcakes_ajax.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;!doctype html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.css&quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;!--[if lte IE 8]&amp;gt;
     &amp;lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.ie.css&quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;![endif]--&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&amp;gt;
    body {
      padding: 0;
      margin: 0;
    }

    html, body, #cupcake-map {
      height: 100%;
    }

  &amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/calvinmetcalf/leaflet-ajax/master/dist/leaflet.ajax.min.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div id=&quot;cupcake-map&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
  var cupcakeTiles = L.tileLayer(&#39;http://a.tiles.mapbox.com/v3/lyzidiamond.map-ietb6srb/{z}/{x}/{y}.png&#39;, {
    maxZoom: 18
  });

  function popUp(feature, layer) {
    layer.bindPopup(feature.properties.name);
  }

  var geojsonLayer = new L.GeoJSON.AJAX(&quot;./cupcakes.json&quot;, {onEachFeature:popUp});

  var map = L.map(&#39;cupcake-map&#39;).fitBounds(geojsonLayer.getBounds());
  cupcakeTiles.addTo(map);
  geojsonLayer.addTo(map);

  &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s different here? A few things. First, notice that instead of the jQuery &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag in the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, I instead added Calvin&amp;rsquo;s Leaflet-Ajax plugin, allowing us to use the methods housed therein. (For more information on Leaflet plugins, click &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/plugins.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.) Second, I made a function popUp that binds a tool tip to each feature (when asked to do so) that displays the text from the &amp;ldquo;name&amp;rdquo; field of the properties of the feature. (This was in our previous example as well, but was not explicitly defined; it was simply an &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Functions_and_function_scope&quot;&gt;anonymous function&lt;/a&gt; being used as a value for the onEachFeature option when adding a new layer. For more info on options when using the Leaflet GeoJSON constructor, check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/reference.html#geojson&quot;&gt;Leaflet API Reference&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, I define a variable geojsonLayer and, using the Leaflet GeoJSON constructor with Calvin&amp;rsquo;s plugin, use the AJAX method, passing in first the location of my GeoJSON file and second the options for the layer, which include setting the onEachFeature method to the popUp function. This means that when any feature in the layer is clicked on, a tool tip with the information defined in the popUp function will show up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then define the map object, tell Leaflet to put it in the div with ID &lt;code&gt;cupcake-map&lt;/code&gt;, fit the bounds of the map to the extend of the features in the GeoJSON layer, add the basemap tiles to the map, and add the GeoJSON layer to the map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this isn&amp;rsquo;t an example of loading JSON from a different domain, but if you look at the GitHub repo for the Leaflet-Ajax tool, there&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/calvinmetcalf/leaflet-ajax/blob/master/example/index.html&quot;&gt;nice little example&lt;/a&gt; showing off this functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wow! That&#39;s a lot of different ways to add GeoJSON to a Leaflet map.&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know, right? Isn&amp;rsquo;t it awesome?! Different techniques will work for different situations, but all of them have some similar features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no need to add a variable definition inside of an external JSON, making it not a true JSON file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using an external GeoJSON file is no problem, and files can be easily switched out at any time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They work!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So go forth, young web cartographers and spatial analysts! Add all the GeoJSON. With these techniques, I think you&amp;rsquo;ll have a ton of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Oh, and. I&amp;rsquo;m always interested in hearing about new techniques and tools. Hit me up on &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/lyzidiamond&quot;&gt;the Twitters&lt;/a&gt; if you find something interesting!)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Commit or Quit</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/commit-or-quit"/>
   <updated>2013-09-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/commit-or-quit</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://b.vimeocdn.com/ts/130/674/130674832_640.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am a perfectionist. Scratch that. I am an &lt;em&gt;ambitious&lt;/em&gt; perfectionist. I want to do everything, and I want to do it perfectly the first time, and I want to do it faster than anyone else has ever done it before. These are unrealistic goals, which means I fail&amp;hellip; a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes the self-doubt, and the shame spiral, and eventually I&amp;rsquo;m sitting in front of a mirror saying over and over again, &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re not good enough. You&amp;rsquo;re never going to be good enough. You suck.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this fun? No. I hate it. Does it make me do more or produce better work? Nope. All it does is waste a lot of time and make me feel terrible about myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m writing code, not making diamonds. Continuing to apply more and more pressure will not produce a better outcome.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dana Jones (@danabrit) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/danabrit/statuses/382127860753784832&quot;&gt;September 23, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I often make this joke around &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com/&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; types, but in seeking to curb this pattern of self-degradation, I have started to follow one basic principle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commit or quit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(If you don&amp;rsquo;t get the git joke, read about making commits &lt;a href=&quot;http://gitref.org/basic/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously. I have made some &lt;em&gt;garbage&lt;/em&gt; commits. Things that broke my entire workflow, things that make my website background bright green, blog posts that are half-written and used as a tool for teaching others about GitHub Pages. And I have learned from every single one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commit or quit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, though, something comes along that I just can&amp;rsquo;t do. I don&amp;rsquo;t have the knowledge yet, or my free time availability is so slim that I know I will be unable to complete a task with the quality it deserves. And I have started to realize that &lt;em&gt;this is okay.&lt;/em&gt; Sometimes quitting is the best solution, as it will better allow you to commit fully to something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commit or quit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This principle applies to other, non-programming aspects of life, too. Just because you have had the same job for five, ten, fifteen years doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you need to stay committed to it. But it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you should beat yourself up for not enjoying it anymore. Taking the time to figure out what you want, knowing that at the end of that discovery you will decide to either commit or quit, which can be liberating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commit or quit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to realize that committing and quitting are not forever. I allow &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; in my life to mean &amp;ldquo;pause temporarily&amp;rdquo; if the situation allows it. I also allow &amp;ldquo;commit&amp;rdquo; to have a variable timeline. The idea is that if you force yourself to make a decision about something, you&amp;rsquo;re taking action and not just &lt;a href=&quot;http://lifehacker.com/the-mistake-smart-people-make-being-in-motion-vs-taki-1143223597&quot;&gt;engaging in motion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commit or quit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the next time you&amp;rsquo;re staring yourself in the mirror, feeling battered by that JavaScript exercise or that error you just can&amp;rsquo;t figure out or that shapefile that won&amp;rsquo;t project correctly no matter what you do, ask yourself if you really can do it. Tell yourself that if you can&amp;rsquo;t, it&amp;rsquo;s okay. But make yourself make a decision. Stop berating yourself in the mirror and pick one: commit or quit. I promise, once you&amp;rsquo;ve made the decision, everything will start to look better.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Adding GeoJSON to Leaflet with Link Relations</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/osgeo-august-meeting"/>
   <updated>2013-08-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/osgeo-august-meeting</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wednesday night, I was fortunate to attend the August meeting of PDX OSGEO, Portland&amp;rsquo;s meetup for open source geo shenanigans. I learned some new stuff, got to see a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mapbox.com/blog/weekend-hack-printing-3d-tiles/&quot;&gt;3D-printed map tile&lt;/a&gt; (!!!!!), and got a chance to show off some of my recent work. The bulk of my contribution to the meeting was showing off a new technique for adding GeoJSON to a Leaflet map. This is an overview of what I talked about, with more detail and background.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com&quot;&gt;Leaflet&lt;/a&gt; is one of the best mapping libraries out there; it&amp;rsquo;s certainly my favorite! But one thing that&amp;rsquo;s somewhat convoluted is adding and using GeoJSON layers inside your Leaflet map. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/reference.html&quot;&gt;Leaflet API&lt;/a&gt; does have a &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/reference.html#geojson&quot;&gt;constructor for adding a GeoJSON layer&lt;/a&gt;, which is great! But when you have a GeoJSON file with hundreds or thousands of features, it makes most sense to house that data in an external file. The challenge then comes when trying to use or reference that file when constructing your map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at an example. (This is the same example I used at the meeting.) A few months ago, my friend Liza tweeted at me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lyzidiamond&quot;&gt;@lyzidiamond&lt;/a&gt; You know maps, right? Is there a website that shows all the places in Portland where cupcakes can be purchased on map? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23serious&amp;amp;src=hash&quot;&gt;#serious&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Liza J (@lizaface) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lizaface/statuses/335503955603890176&quot;&gt;May 17, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And so, with all of my infinite free time*, I set off to construct a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lyzidiamond/lyzidiamond.github.com/blob/master/cupcakes.json&quot;&gt;GeoJSON file&lt;/a&gt; of places to buy cupcakes in Portland. &lt;em&gt;(Disclaimer: It&amp;rsquo;s not comprehensive and it&amp;rsquo;s not at all done, so expect it to change significantly and frequently.)&lt;/em&gt; But when I set off to create my map, I ran into the problem of referencing this file. How was I to assign the data to a variable such that I could use it in the L.geoJson constructor and add it as a layer to my map?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically when I have an issue like this, I turn to the best tech support at my disposal: Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Question: What is the best way to reference an external geojson file for use in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LeafletJS&quot;&gt;@LeafletJS&lt;/a&gt; map? Do I assign to a variable in the file?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Lyzi Diamond (@lyzidiamond) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lyzidiamond/statuses/364169343854059520&quot;&gt;August 4, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The folks at Leaflet agreed that this would be the best way to go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lyzidiamond&quot;&gt;@lyzidiamond&lt;/a&gt; yep, it&amp;#39;s the simplest way if you&amp;#39;re including the GeoJSON statically on page load&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Leaflet (@LeafletJS) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LeafletJS/statuses/364336552383492097&quot;&gt;August 5, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of my Twitter friends, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/sgillies&quot;&gt;Sean Gillies&lt;/a&gt;, had another suggestion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lyzidiamond&quot;&gt;@lyzidiamond&lt;/a&gt; Fwiw, we use a typed link at ISAW: &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/Ea2MzuchBV&quot;&gt;http://t.co/Ea2MzuchBV&lt;/a&gt;. If you don&amp;#39;t want an extra request, you can use a data uri.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sean Gillies (@sgillies) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sgillies/statuses/364171433246588928&quot;&gt;August 4, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I decided to play with this a little more, and it totally worked! And it worked well! So let&amp;rsquo;s talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;GeoJSON: The Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JSON and GeoJSON files are just JavaScript files. (JSON stands for JavaScript Object Notation; you can read more about JSON as a file type in a previous post, &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/github-geojson/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.) As such, you can reference a JSON or GeoJSON file as a script, the same way you would for, say, including the Leaflet or jQuery libraries in your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script src=&quot;./cupcakes.json&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding a link to a script allows you access to its content; it&amp;rsquo;s as if you copy-pasted the code in the script into your HTML file. Everything that is in that file is now effectively inside your HTML file and can be referenced and used freely. Adding the GeoJSON at the top does the same thing, but the GeoJSON data has no name. It&amp;rsquo;s not attached to a variable. It&amp;rsquo;s just features that can&amp;rsquo;t be referenced, containing geometry and properties that can&amp;rsquo;t be referenced. For the purposes of our map, it is essentially useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious solution is to add a variable definition to our cupcakes.json file. That would mean that instead of this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
  &quot;type&quot;: &quot;FeatureCollection&quot;,
  &quot;features&quot;: [
    {
      &quot;type&quot;: &quot;Feature&quot;,
      &quot;geometry&quot;: {
        &quot;type&quot;: &quot;Point&quot;,
        &quot;coordinates&quot;: [
          -122.65335738658904,
          45.512083676585156
        ]
      },
      &quot;properties&quot;: {
          &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Hungry Heart Cupcakes&quot;,
          &quot;address&quot;: &quot;1212 SE Hawthorne Boulevard&quot;,
          &quot;website&quot;: &quot;http://www.hungryheartcupcakes.com&quot;,
          &quot;gluten free&quot;: &quot;no&quot;,
          &quot;open1&quot;: &quot;Monday - Sunday, 11am - 9pm&quot;
      }
    },

...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we would have something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var cupcakes = {
  &quot;type&quot;: &quot;FeatureCollection&quot;,
  &quot;features&quot;: [
    {
      &quot;type&quot;: &quot;Feature&quot;,
      &quot;geometry&quot;: {
        &quot;type&quot;: &quot;Point&quot;,
        &quot;coordinates&quot;: [
          -122.65335738658904,
          45.512083676585156
        ]
      },
      &quot;properties&quot;: {
          &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Hungry Heart Cupcakes&quot;,
          &quot;address&quot;: &quot;1212 SE Hawthorne Boulevard&quot;,
          &quot;website&quot;: &quot;http://www.hungryheartcupcakes.com&quot;,
          &quot;gluten free&quot;: &quot;no&quot;,
          &quot;open1&quot;: &quot;Monday - Sunday, 11am - 9pm&quot;
      }
    },

...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would totally work, but it would mean that our cupcakes.json file would no longer be a true JSON/GeoJSON file. If you tried to &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/github-geojson-gets-better/&quot;&gt;show the file in GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, for example, the points would not be interpreted and a map would not be rendered. Additionally, you don&amp;rsquo;t always have direct control over the GeoJSON file itself, especially if it&amp;rsquo;s a shared dataset or if it&amp;rsquo;s being returned from some other process. Adding a variable definition could also potentially mess up the work of anyone else trying to use your dataset, if it is indeed a dataset you constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can you do? You can used a typed link/link relation and a little bit of jQuery. It&amp;rsquo;s really quite magical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;GeoJSON and Leaflet: The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the code, and then talk through it. You can view a live version of this &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.com/cupcakes.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.css&quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&amp;gt;
  body {  padding: 0; margin: 0;  }
  html, body, #cupcake-map {  height: 100%;  }
  &amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script src=&quot;http://code.jquery.com/jquery-1.10.2.min.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;link rel=&quot;points&quot; type=&quot;application/json&quot; href=&quot;./cupcakes.json&quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div id=&quot;cupcake-map&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
  var cupcakeTiles = L.tileLayer(&#39;http://a.tiles.mapbox.com/v3/lyzidiamond.map-ietb6srb/{z}/{x}/{y}.png&#39;, {
    maxZooom: 18  
  });

  $.getJSON($(&#39;link[rel=&quot;points&quot;]&#39;).attr(&quot;href&quot;), function(data) {
    var geojson = L.geoJson(data, {
      onEachFeature: function (feature, layer) {
        layer.bindPopup(feature.properties.name);
      }
    });
    var map = L.map(&#39;cupcake-map&#39;).fitBounds(geojson.getBounds());
    cupcakeTiles.addTo(map);
    geojson.addTo(map);
  });
  &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Head&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaflet, as discussed previously, is a JavaScript mapping library with a lot of great functionality. (For more info on getting started with and using Leaflet, check out their &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/examples/quick-start.html&quot;&gt;Quick Start Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.) In order to use it, we need to include both a Leaflet CSS file (for map styling) and the Leaflet JavaScript file, which is what the stylesheet on line 3 and the script on line 8 are all about. Lines 4 through 7 are CSS rules to give our map a height and ensure that it is actually full-screen on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.css&quot; /&amp;gt;
...
&amp;lt;script src=&quot;http://cdn.leafletjs.com/leaflet-0.5/leaflet.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other library we need to make this work is called &lt;a href=&quot;http://jquery.com/&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt;. jQuery is a JavaScript library that can make developing way easier, as it takes some of the complicated parts of the language and synthesizes them into easy-to-use pieces. Line 9 includes jQuery in our map, which allows us to use its functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &amp;lt;script src=&quot;http://code.jquery.com/jquery-1.10.2.min.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting part comes at Line 10. This is where we are including our JSON** file using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.whatwg.org/the-road-to-html-5-link-relations&quot;&gt;link relation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &amp;lt;link rel=&quot;points&quot; type=&quot;application/json&quot; href=&quot;./cupcakes.json&quot;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As defined on the WHATWG blog post to which I just linked, &amp;ldquo;Regular links simply point to another page. Link relations are a way to explain &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you&amp;rsquo;re pointing to another page. They finish the sentence, &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;m pointing to this other page because&amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typcailly, link relations are used with a common set of keywords that have specific value to the browser. For example, our CSS stylesheet on line 3 has the link relation &lt;code&gt;rel=&amp;ldquo;stylesheet&amp;rdquo;&lt;/code&gt;. This is the most common link relation, and every browser knows to download the data from the link before loading the page, as the relation tells it that the linked data contains important style information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case, we are sort of hacking around that. We don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily want the browser to fetch the data on load or at any particular time. Indeed, we don&amp;rsquo;t want the browser to do anything with our GeoJSON file until we tell it to. Thus, we supply the link with a &lt;code&gt;rel=&amp;ldquo;points&amp;rdquo;&lt;/code&gt;, which isn&amp;rsquo;t going to have any unintended consequences. (For more information on link relation keywords and what they do, check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://microformats.org/wiki/existing-rel-values&quot;&gt;this comprehensive list&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Body&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s get into the body of our HTML. The first think you see on line 13 is an empty div with id &amp;ldquo;cupcake-map.&amp;rdquo; This is how Leaflet works: you create an empty div, and then write some JavaScript to fill it in. For us, this JavaScript starts on the very next line, as it&amp;rsquo;s a full-screen web map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div id=&quot;cupcake-map&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our JavaScript is sandwiched between &lt;code&gt;script&lt;/code&gt; tags, which lets the browser know that anything inside of them is JavaScript and should be treated as such. (This was mirrored in lines 4 and 7 in the head, with &lt;code&gt;style&lt;/code&gt; tags.) The first thing we do in our script (line 15) is define a variable called cupcakeTiles, and use the Leaflet &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/reference.html#tilelayer&quot;&gt;tileLayer&lt;/a&gt; constructor to define a map tile layer (more info on that at the link). This map uses custom tiles I made using &lt;a href=&quot;http://mapbox.com&quot;&gt;MapBox&lt;/a&gt;, so this constructor links to those tiles. It also adds a property for maxZoom, ensuring that the map will not be zoomed in past zoom level 18. (For more information on web maps and zoom levels and how they work, check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mapbox.com/developers/guide/&quot;&gt;this excellent blog post&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Line 19 is where the code gets interesting, as we employ jQuery&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.getJSON/&quot;&gt;getJSON method&lt;/a&gt;. This method takes three parameters: A URL of the location of the data, a plain object or string that gets sent with the request for the data, and a function to execute if the request for data is successful. The second parameter is optional, and you&amp;rsquo;ll see we don&amp;rsquo;t actually use it in our example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; $.getJSON($(&#39;link[rel=&quot;points&quot;]&#39;).attr(&quot;href&quot;), function(data) {
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pass &lt;code&gt;$(&amp;lsquo;link[rel=&amp;ldquo;points&amp;rdquo;]&amp;rsquo;).attr(&amp;ldquo;href&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/code&gt; as our first parameter, which actually &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; translate to a URL. It finds a link by its rel value (&lt;code&gt;$(&amp;lsquo;link[rel=&amp;ldquo;points&amp;rdquo;]&amp;rsquo;)&lt;/code&gt;), and then uses a getter method &lt;a href=&quot;http://api.jquery.com/attr/&quot;&gt;attr&lt;/a&gt; to pull the value of the href parameter in the link. This returns &lt;code&gt;&amp;ldquo;./cupcakes.json&amp;rdquo;&lt;/code&gt;, which is the location of our JSON file. (I should also note that our link has an attribute &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; that is defined as &lt;code&gt;&amp;lsquo;application/json&amp;rsquo;&lt;/code&gt;. This helps the browser understand that the data in the link is JSON and should be treated as such.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second parameter is actually a function to be executed upon successful retrieval of data, called a &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/js-ctypes/js-ctypes_reference/Callbacks&quot;&gt;callback function&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. (If that blows your mind, take some time to read about &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asynchronous_I/O&quot;&gt;asynchronous programming&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s really fascinating.) We actually have housed all the rest of the map creation and layer adding functionality of our map inside of this callback function, which ensures that the map won&amp;rsquo;t draw unless the GeoJSON has sucecssfully been retrieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our callback function takes one parameter, data, which will be the data that&amp;rsquo;s returned from the getJSON method. The first thing the function does is create a variable geojson and use the Leaflet &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/reference.html#geojson&quot;&gt;geoJson&lt;/a&gt; constructor to define a GeoJSON layer. The constructor takes two parameters: one for the actual GeoJSON that will make the layer (data, in our case), and any options you wish to specify. One of thse is called &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/reference.html#geojson-oneachfeature&quot;&gt;onEachFeature&lt;/a&gt;, which is most commonly used for attaching popups to data. That&amp;rsquo;s how we used it, anyway! As the value for onEachFeature, we define a function that takes our data and adds a popup to each feature that shows whatever value is in that feature&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;name&amp;rdquo; property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$.getJSON($(&#39;link[rel=&quot;points&quot;]&#39;).attr(&quot;href&quot;), function(data) {
    var geojson = L.geoJson(data, {
      onEachFeature: function (feature, layer) {
        layer.bindPopup(feature.properties.name);
      }
    });
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we have defined our GeoJSON layer, we have to actually create our map. This is done on line 23, where we create a variable map and use the Leaflet &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/reference.html#map-class&quot;&gt;map&lt;/a&gt; constructor to put our map in the &amp;ldquo;cupcake-map&amp;rdquo; div. We then also add a method &lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com/reference.html#map-fitbounds&quot;&gt;fitBounds()&lt;/a&gt; and pass it the extent of our GeoJSON data, which sets the bounds of our map to match the bounds of our data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last two lines are pretty self-explanatory: we add our cupcakeTiles layer to the map and we add our geojson layer to the map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$.getJSON($(&#39;link[rel=&quot;points&quot;]&#39;).attr(&quot;href&quot;), function(data) {
  var geojson = L.geoJson(data, {
    onEachFeature: function (feature, layer) {
      layer.bindPopup(feature.properties.name);
    }
  });
  var map = L.map(&#39;cupcake-map&#39;).fitBounds(geojson.getBounds());
  cupcakeTiles.addTo(map);
  geojson.addTo(map);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;We did it!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what did we just do? We made a map with custom tiles that grabs GeoJSON from an external file without changing that file. Oh, and we added some popups to the GeoJSON features and set the bounds of our map to match the bounds of the data. Not too bad for 29 lines of code!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.github.com/lyzidiamond/lyzidiamond.github.com/master/images/cupcakes.PNG&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;*This is a joke.&lt;br&gt;
**JSON and GeoJSON are just JavaScript objects. A GeoJSON file can be saved as type .geojson, .json, or .js. All of them work.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>geojson.io: In-browser spatial data creation and sharing. Finally.</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/geojson-io"/>
   <updated>2013-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/geojson-io</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;http://giscollective.org&quot;&gt;GIS Collective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://giscollective.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/geojsonio1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mapbox.com/blog/geojsonio-announce/&quot;&gt;its blog&lt;/a&gt;, the open-source geo wizard repository &lt;a href=&quot;http://mapbox.com/&quot;&gt;MapBox&lt;/a&gt; has announced a new project to create, share, and edit geospatial data in your browser. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;http://geojson.io&quot;&gt;geojson.io&lt;/a&gt;, and it’s set to sweep the nation! Or at least, the nation of those who like creating, sharing and editing spatial data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, the product (so far) has the following features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw points, lines, or polygons on the Leaflet map and receive GeoJSON output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edit data attributes in table or JSON format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edit GeoJSON files and gists containing GeoJSON from &lt;a href=&quot;http://giscollective.org/github-and-geojson-just-keeps-getting-better/&quot;&gt;GitHub repositories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upload a file in one several formats for conversion to GeoJSON*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is also a &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/geojsonio/oibjgofbhldcajfamjganpeacipebckp&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; (for all you &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; users out there) that adds a button to GitHub repos and gists containing geojson for easy editing in geojson.io. This has huge implications for data collaboration; the two datasets mentioned in the MapBox post are &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/benbalter/dc-wifi-social&quot;&gt;bars that have free wi-fi&lt;/a&gt; (currently a Washington, DC-focused dataset) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://geojson.io/#gist:6188907&quot;&gt;favorite running routes&lt;/a&gt;. The possibilities are endless! What data will you create?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is open source, which means that anyone can add to it and help make it better! To contribute, &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/fork-a-repo&quot;&gt;fork&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mapbox/geojson.io&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; and have at it. Remember: with open source, no contribution is too small! For more information on contributing to open source projects and open source in general, check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://opensource.com/resources/what-open-source&quot;&gt;this great explanation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Still unsure about GeoJSON? Not entirely sure what GitHub is? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://giscollective.org/github-bringing-geojson-to-life-since-2013/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Local Governments and Open Data</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/local-gov-open-data"/>
   <updated>2013-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/local-gov-open-data</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wrote this on Facebook the other day, and my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/mapadelphia&quot;&gt;Sarah&lt;/a&gt; asked me to write it as a blog post so she could share it with others. I do agree that it&amp;rsquo;s something others need to read: local governments aren&amp;rsquo;t going to move toward shared/open data models until a) they&amp;rsquo;ve received funding to do so, or b) they&amp;rsquo;re convinced it&amp;rsquo;s mutually beneficial. The latter is likelier than the former. Let&amp;rsquo;s start some conversations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lanecounty.org/departments/sheriff/office/emermgmt/documents/nhmp2011femareview2.pdf&quot;&gt;Lane County Natural Hazard Mitigation Plan 2012 Update&lt;/a&gt; [PDF]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Although there is regional agreement about the benefits of a centralized location for storing map related metadata, the county and most cities opt to maintain their own data. Achieving a single, regional location for accessing accurate GIS data is not a high priority for agencies facing shrinking budgets and decreasing staff resources. A regional repository would require dedicated staff to locate, update, create and maintain metadata on an ongoing basis. Lane Council of Governments has twice applied for grant funding for this project but funding was not awarded. This project is repeated each year in Lane Council of Governments&#39; annual list of top five projects but remains unfunded.&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a common argument. Too common. Hard work up front saves time in repetition and data creation later. Robust and open data is the only path to the future. The only one.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Geographic Data Assumptions: MAUP and Ecological Fallacies</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/geographic-data-assumptions"/>
   <updated>2013-07-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/geographic-data-assumptions</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;http://giscollective.org&quot;&gt;GIS Collective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are generally adept at critical thinking and deductive reasoning. We tend to understand the world around us fairly easily, because the world operates on a few basic principles. By relying on these principles, we can find the signals through the noise (or at least narrow it down to a few options). To do this, we tend to rely on assumption and inference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a good thing. It allows us to, for example, use words that others may not have heard before without having to explain them explicitly. One could deduce that “polygamy” probably means marriage to multiple people, because “monogamy” is the marriage (hah) of the Greek words &lt;em&gt;monos&lt;/em&gt; (one) and &lt;em&gt;gamos&lt;/em&gt; (marriage), and the Greek word &lt;em&gt;polys&lt;/em&gt; means many. You don’t have to look it up, and because you’ve seen the word “monogamy” so many times, you understand “polygamy” in context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maps are a little different. Modern society has allowed for the growth of spatial literacy, and with maps in our pockets (yes, on the cell phones), we do a pretty good job of navigating using lines and cardinal directions. As such, we feel we are qualified to learn about the world in a spatial way, which many of us are! But it’s important to know about the ways that maps can distort our understanding of data, such that we can challenge our assumptions in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1991, Mark Monmonier wrote a book called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/How-Lie-Maps-2nd-Edition/dp/0226534219&quot;&gt;“How to Lie With Maps.”&lt;/a&gt; The book remains essential to any geographic information science curriculum, and for those interested in learning more about the subjects I’m going to touch on here, it’s a great resource. The first paragraph of the introduction reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not only is it easy to lie with maps, it’s essential. To portray meaningful relationships for a complex, three-dimensional world on a flat sheet of paper or a video screen, a map must distort reality. As a scale model, the map must use symbols that almost always are proportionally much bigger or thicker than the features they represent. To avoid hiding critical information in a fog of detail, the map must offer a selective, incomplete view of reality. There’s no escape from the cartographic paradox: to present a useful and truthful picture, an accurate map must tell white lies.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s the first thing to realize: &lt;strong&gt;every map is lying to you all the time&lt;/strong&gt;. In an ideal world, the map is lying to you in the hopes of conveying the most information to you that it possibly can, but sometimes maps make generalizations and approximations for sake of the cartographer and not the map’s intended audience. Let’s take a look at an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://giscollective.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/maup2.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a map from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/politics/election-map-2012/president/&quot;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt; showing the results of the 2012 presidential election. Considering that presidential races in this country are decided by the electoral college, and each state’s electors all vote for the same candidate, breaking out the data state by state makes sense. Nevada is blue, Mississippi is red, Obama won the election, let’s all go get a beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this map doesn’t tell the whole story. Let’s look at another map from the Washington Post of the exact same data, just aggregated differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://giscollective.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/maup3.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevada doesn’t look as blue as it did in the previous map, and Mississippi doesn’t look quite as red. By grouping data by states, the map was hiding some of the complexity in the data, causing the reader to make certain assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a common and well-documented spatial data visualization circumstance called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modifiable_areal_unit_problem&quot;&gt;modifiable areal unit problem&lt;/a&gt;, often acronomized as MAUP. First identified by Gehlke and Biehl in 1934, the MAUP is a statistical bias that is influenced by both the means in which point-based data is aggregated, and the districts into which that data is grouped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presidential election maps above were (in theory*) generated from point-based data: one vote, one point. But showing 117 million points on a map would take a really long time and it wouldn’t be that useful (plus, it’s a cartographic nightmare). The cartographer is all but obligated to aggregate and group the data for ease of consumption, but every grouping mechanism is going to present its own challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I live in Portland, which is in Multnomah County, Oregon. In the 2012 election, Multnomah County had 367,992 ballots cast in 132 precincts. (Oregon has vote by mail, so that changes things around a bit geographically, but that’s not super relevant here.) 75.37% of the votes cast for president were cast for Barack Obama. When you look at Multnomah County on the presidential map above, you’ll see that it’s pretty blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://giscollective.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/maup4.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is that map telling you what’s really going on beneath the aggregation? Nope. Could one theoretically assume that all 367,992 ballots in Multnomah County were cast for Obama? Sure. Does it matter? In this case, probably not that much for you and me, but if you’re interested in conducting a political campaign, the MAUP could seriously hinder your strategy: &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; if you only have access to aggregated data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assumption falls into a category of assumptions called &lt;strong&gt;ecological fallacies&lt;/strong&gt;. Ecological fallacies fall into four camps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confusion between ecological correlations and individual correlations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confusion between group average and total average&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simpson’s Paradox (when comparing two populations divided in groups of different sizes, the average of some variable in the first population can be higher in every group and yet lower in the total population)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confusion between higher average and higher likelihood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Believe it or not, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecological_fallacy&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; does a really great job breaking each of these down. If you’re interested in learning more about the specifics, head over there.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ecological fallacies and modifiable areal unit problems go hand in hand: the methods for aggregating the data tend to highlight certain trends that are potentially damaging to true understanding (MAUP), and the conclusions drawn from the aggregated data can be erroneous (ecological fallacies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where this is really important is in the realm of public policy. Every policy proposal comes with a statistical analysis of need, or a statistical analysis of effectiveness based on geographic data (that’s why we have a census, y’all), and then an analysis and conclusions drawn from that data. But if the only data available for a specific metric is aggregated into neighborhoods, or census tracts, or zip codes, or watersheds, or any other group, are we really getting the whole story? Are the assumptions we’re making about the data correct?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I tell people I make maps for a living, one of the most common responses is, “That’s still a job? Isn’t everything already mapped?”** Although it’s an extremely irritating and silly question, answering it several times has brought me to this conclusion: data display and design issues (MAUP) and the problems with data understanding (ecological fallacies), along with many other things, make data visualization a fascinating (and extremely relevant) science. I believe it is the job of the cartographer to understand the assumptions that will be made when users try to interpret her product, to try and provide as much data as possible, and to be as up front and honest about the ways in which the data is distorted by visualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maps, just like any other information graphic, exist to show signals in the noise. We as cartographers should work hard to identify common assumptions and work &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; them to tell accurate and interesting stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;* This is likely false. Election data is aggregated by polling place/ward/district/whatever grouping system is employed where you live. Which creates its own statistical data aggregation problems, no?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;** I usually come up with two disparate geographic datasets that are so laughably separate that nobody would ever map them together, and talk about how cool it would be if they were juxtaposed. Like, a map of New York City showing art galleries overlayed with National Flood Insurance Program policy holders. If you’re interested in those sorts of strange map mashups, check out Rebecca Solint’s book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Infinite-City-San-Francisco-Atlas/dp/052026506&quot;&gt;Infinite City: A San Francisco Atlas.&amp;ldquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GitHub and GeoJSON: Just Keeps Getting Better</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/github-geojson-gets-better"/>
   <updated>2013-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/github-geojson-gets-better</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;http://giscollective.org&quot;&gt;GIS Collective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://giscollective.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/cluster.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;GitHub has announced today some &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/blog/1541-geojson-rendering-improvements&quot;&gt;new features&lt;/a&gt; for rendering geographic data, coming off its announcement two weeks ago that GeoJSON data would now be displayed on a map when opened inside a repo. These changes show that the folks over at GitHub are serious about the importance of geospatial, and recognize that more of the world’s developers are turning to maps and coordinates as a way to display, communicate, and analyze data. Spatial is special once again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      GitHub now supports rendering &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbostock/topojson&quot;&gt;TopoJSON&lt;/a&gt;, an extension of GeoJSON that encodes topology and can be up to 80% smaller than their GeoJSON equivalents.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Starting today, you don’t have to rename geo files with a new extension. GitHub will now render GeoJSON (and TopoJSON) in all &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/search?q=extension%3Ageojson&amp;type=Code&amp;ref=searchresults&quot;&gt;.geojson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/search?q=extension%3Atopojson&amp;type=Code&amp;s=&quot;&gt;.topojson&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/search?q=FeatureCollection+extension%3Ajson&amp;type=Code&amp;s=indexed&quot;&gt;.json&lt;/a&gt; files.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      Complex geographic datasets can often be difficult to visualize, especially if points are grouped close together. We now &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Leaflet/Leaflet.markercluster&quot;&gt;automatically cluster&lt;/a&gt; nearby markers, allowing us to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/benbalter/dc-maps&quot;&gt;better support&lt;/a&gt; larger datasets.
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also now use the rendered map and embed it elsewhere, which is great if you want a quick geographic visualization! Head over to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/blog/1541-geojson-rendering-improvements&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt; to read more, and let’s get some more geogeeks on the GitHubs!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GitHub: Bringing GeoJSON To Life Since 2013</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/github-geojson"/>
   <updated>2013-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/github-geojson</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post originally appeared on &lt;a href=&quot;http://giscollective.org&quot;&gt;GIS Collective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://giscollective.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/githubgeojson1.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last week, the code repository heroes over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; made an awesome announcement: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/blog/1528-there-s-a-map-for-that&quot;&gt;Any .geojson files living in GitHub repos will now be rendered on a Leaflet-driven, OSM tile-backed map right inside of GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, with tooltips showing the data properties to boot! This is a truly exciting moment for all geonerds who code, developers who use geodata, and everyone in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hey, wait a minute,” you may be saying. “What is GitHub again? And &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geojson.org/&quot;&gt;GeoJSON&lt;/a&gt;… I think I’ve heard of that, but what is it for?” Do not fret! We at GISC know that the field is moving quickly, and we are happy to provide guidance and direction for your geospatial journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Git and GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;




&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.palermo.edu/Archivos_content/ingenieria/top/130712_git_github_topdenota1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before learning about GitHub, we first have to understand &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;. Git is a tool that allows multiple people to work on the same files at the same time without overwriting each other’s changes. This general concept is called &lt;em&gt;version control&lt;/em&gt;, and git is a &lt;em&gt;version control system&lt;/em&gt;. There are several other version control systems out there, but git is popular because it does its job more efficiently than many (if not all) of the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for multiple people to work on a project, the data has to live in a place where multiple people can access it, right? GitHub is that place: the site houses thousands and thousands of projects, in individual workspaces called &lt;em&gt;repositories&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;repos&lt;/em&gt;, that multiple people can access, copy, edit, and update using the tools available via git. These repositories also have a tracking element; when someone makes a change to a project, or a &lt;em&gt;commit&lt;/em&gt;, information is stored about the user, the time, the exact changes that were made (all the way down to the individual line inside the file!), and a unique ID that allows the project owner to restore back to that particular moment. It’s pretty effing cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because git is so great, and GitHub is so popular, people have been using it for all kinds of projects, coding and otherwise. I have seen professors put lectures and lecture notes on GitHub, several of my friends use it as a place to work on resumes and terminal projects… you can basically use it for anything. Shoot, even the code for my website lives on GitHub. So it follows that with the advent of mapping and geospatial analysis on the web, there is a lot of geodata housed on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;GeoJSON&lt;/h2&gt;




&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://giscollective.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/geojson.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the more common formats used for geospatial data in web mapping applications is called &lt;em&gt;GeoJSON&lt;/em&gt;. GeoJSON was born out of a format called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://json.org&quot;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, which stands for JavaScript Object Notation. JSON is like a table turned on its side; each row gets its own section, and inside of that section is a series of properties and values unique to that row. For example, a table of Presidents of the United States might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://giscollective.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/presidents.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In JSON, the table might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  “presidents” : {
    “name” : “Barack Obama”,
      “hometown” : “Honolulu, HI”,
      “number” : “44”,
      “year elected” : “2008”,
      “terms served” : “2”,
      “child1” : {
        “name” : “Malia”,
        “born” : “1998”
      },
      “child2” : {
        “name” : “Sasha”,
        “born” : “2001”
      }
    },
    {
      “name” : “George W. Bush”,
      “hometown” : “New Haven, CT”,
      “number” : “43”,
      “year elected” : “2000”,
      “terms served” : “2”,
      “child1” : {
        “name” : “Jenna”,
        “born” : “1981”
      },
      “child2” : {
        “name” : “Barbara”,
        “born” : “1981”
      }
    }&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GeoJSON takes this format and adds geometry, allowing mapping engines and libraries to parse the data and place these objects in space using coordinates, as well as properties, which can be thought of like the fields and values in an attribute table. GeoJSON allows for points, lines, polygons, and a few other data types, but it’s all formatted in much the same way as the JSON example, above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many if not all of the open source mapping libraries for JavaScript (&lt;a href=&quot;http://leafletjs.com&quot;&gt;Leaflet&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://mapbox.com&quot;&gt;MapBox&lt;/a&gt; most notably) support GeoJSON and allow GeoJSON layers to be added to their maps. &lt;a href=&quot;http://qgis.org&quot;&gt;QGIS&lt;/a&gt;, the open source desktop mapping application, also allows the user to view and export data in the GeoJSON format. This has made it extremely popular as a geodata format, which is why it shows up frequently on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;In Summary&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So now that we know what GitHub is used for and how GeoJSON works, we can clearly see why GitHub’s announcement last week was such a big deal: If you click on any .geojson file in a repo on github.com, the data will be rendered and displayed on a map. No more scrolling through text and trying to figure out where [45.528402,-122.65762] might be, because all of the data is displayed spatially for easy perusal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With limited time and limited space, I can only say so much, so this wasn’t a thorough walkthrough of git, GitHub, or GeoJSON. I didn’t even touch Leaflet or &lt;a href=&quot;http://openstreetmap.org&quot;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; — posts going into all of these things in depth will be on the blog in the coming weeks. For now, head on over to GitHub, find some GeoJSON files, check out the sweet maps, and maybe try making your own repo! And please stay tuned for more updates — by the end of the summer, you’re going to be using git like a pro!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Remembering an Old Friend</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/stephen-person"/>
   <updated>2013-06-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/stephen-person</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Stephen Alan Person, one of my very good friends, passed away from injuries sustained in a drunk driving incident on Tuesday, May 28, 2013. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to write about him since it happened, but it&amp;rsquo;s been so difficult. This is my first attempt, some assorted thoughts on the passing of a special man who touched a lot of lives. Stephen, I miss you so much. I can&amp;rsquo;t wait for all of the adventures we&amp;rsquo;ll have again someday. You&amp;rsquo;re in my thoughts always.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen was one of the most amazing people I have ever met. I feel like people tend to say these things about their friends upon their passing, and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s always true, but I feel like this case is particular. It would take more than the fingers of two hands to count all the times Stephen showed up in random places, when I was with random groups of people, and there was never an awkward moment. He got along with everyone, it was so easy, and everyone loved him. I have so many stories about him, with him. That&amp;rsquo;s what I keep holding on to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point, back when we first met, we decided we were going to write a radio drama. I think I was really into radio dramas at the time. One day when we were sitting in his living room in that ridiculous house on Patterson Alley and came up with CONSTITUTIONBOT, a character for our radio show who is a robot programmed to enforce the constitution. I remember Stephen in the backyard pantomiming stiff arms saying, &amp;ldquo;I AM DUE PROCESS&amp;rdquo; in a robot voice. I can hear it and I can hear him laugh about it. It makes me laugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the time we drove down to the bay for spring break in 2010 and he taught us all how to play &amp;ldquo;Cows On My Side.&amp;rdquo; And we went to In-N-Out and he ate a ridiculous amount of hamburger and we sat on the roof of my car and smoked cigarettes. When I got us lost in San Francisco on the way to Oddsac but then Stephen hung out with Avey Tare in a bar anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See, Stephen could get himself into the craziest situations. He always met the band, he was always on the list, the bands always stayed at his house. When I first moved to Portland, he was pretty much the only dude I hung out with. We stood in front of Old Wives Tales protesting the poor management. We ate burritos and played ping pong and sat in his backyard. I ran into him all over town. When I was visiting Portland last April for the interview that landed me my current job, I realized I only had my presentation in Google Docs and not on a thumb drive, and what if the office didn&amp;rsquo;t have internet? So Stephen and I went to the Duck Store in the White Stag building, bought a thumb drive, went up to the fourth floor studio and used one of the computers to put the presentation on it. He rode the MAX with me to my interview, gave me a quick squeeze and a &amp;ldquo;Good luck!&amp;rdquo; and headed on his way. He was the first person to text me after my interview to see how it went. He was the first person I texted when I got the job, the job I still have today that has propelled me forward in my career. Without Stephen, it may never have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started writing this last week, before his memorial, and now that I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to so many of his friends and people close to him, I realize that we all have these stories. Stephen loved all of us for exactly who we are. He found the things we love about ourselves and made those the things important. He celebrated our successes and helped us move past our failures. Stephen never judged me. Stephen was always there for me. Stephen was our biggest cheerleader. And we are all better for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the memorial, when I was tired of trying to cry quietly in my seat, I stepped outside and listened to some of the old voicemails Stephen had left me. Some of them were silly, some involved descriptions of what he was looking at while he was leaving the message. A staggering number of them are they same: &amp;ldquo;Hey Lyzi, this is Stephen. I, ah, haven&amp;rsquo;t seen you in a few weeks and was wondering how you&amp;rsquo;ve been, if you wanna kick it. So, ah, call me back!&amp;rdquo; Stephen cared so much about his friends, he went out of his way to make sure he spoke to us regularly. To make sure he was at every show. To celebrate the things about us that are special. He noticed every one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to live my life like Stephen lived his: letting people know he cared about them, talking to strangers, telling jokes, helping out, being honest, being true, never being bored, never giving up, always learning, always creating, growing, giving. In his life, Stephen changed mine. I miss him so much, but I know he&amp;rsquo;s still around us all the time, every time we help out a friend, every time we make up a silly song, and every time we stop a stranger on the street, asking him to tell us a joke.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Getting a Good (GIS) Job, Part 1</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/getting-a-good-job-pt-1"/>
   <updated>2013-05-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/getting-a-good-job-pt-1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, I was asked by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://orurisayp.org&quot;&gt;ORURISA Young Professionals&lt;/a&gt; to give a short talk about the transition from completing a geogrpahy or GIS degree to becoming employed in the field of geospatial. There were around eight of us who gave short talks, and each of us had good pieces of advice to share. I thought the whole thing was very valuable, albeit poorly-attended, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to attempt to recreate some of that advice here. Although the talk was GIS-oriented and some of the conversation was specific to geospatial careers, I feel that a lot of the advice is applicable to job hunters regardless of field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 1 is included here. Parts 2, 3, and 4 will be included in future blog posts, which I will link to from this blog post when they&amp;rsquo;re up.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Part 1: Taking Stock&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Life Inventory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, and it sounds like most people, the hardest part about applying for jobs is &lt;strong&gt;actually sitting down and starting.&lt;/strong&gt; You don&amp;rsquo;t know what to include, you can&amp;rsquo;t remember the full scope of that project you worked on junior year that would be &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; to include in this cover letter, etc. One thing that helped me get started when I was looking for a job was to do a little &lt;strong&gt;life inventory&lt;/strong&gt;. I opened a Google Doc and started writing down everything about me: skills I have, projects I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on, jobs I&amp;rsquo;ve had, volunteer experiences, interests (both personal and professional), places I&amp;rsquo;ve lived, everything. &lt;em&gt;This inventory became my repository for job applications, and remains to this day.&lt;/em&gt; Whenever I do something new, I put it in the inventory for posterity, and whenever I&amp;rsquo;m applying to a job, this list is the first place I go. Your list does not have to be organized at all at first; just add stuff to it as it comes to mind. Whenever you feel like you have some time and want to tackle it, you can organize your thoughts into some categories. My categories are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things I&amp;rsquo;ve Made/Written&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things I&amp;rsquo;ve Done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skills (Proficiency)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skills (Experience)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jobs I&amp;rsquo;ve Had&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volunteer Experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Places I&amp;rsquo;ve Been&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keyword Interests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;skills&lt;/strong&gt; sections are broken into skills I am proficient at and skills I have touched on or have some experience with, but about which I would not label myself as proficient. The &amp;ldquo;Things I&amp;rsquo;ve Made/Written&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Things I&amp;rsquo;ve Done&amp;rdquo; sections are separated because the former includes &lt;strong&gt;tangible portfolio pieces&lt;/strong&gt;, whereas the latter focuses on &lt;strong&gt;experiences&lt;/strong&gt;. I also broke apart jobs and volunteer experienecs, although I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily divide them  by whether or not I received monetary compensation; for me, jobs are the long-term positions where I&amp;rsquo;ve been responsible for a project or a portion of the project, whereas volunteer experience encompasses mostly periodic volunteering and/or areas that are not relevant to my career. The &amp;ldquo;Keyword Interests&amp;rdquo; section is the newest section, and contains a list of both my &lt;strong&gt;personal and professional interests&lt;/strong&gt; in one- to three-word items. This is mostly a personal exercise: I should be able to look at any item on that list and talk about why I am interested in it, what aspects of it interest me, and how it relates to the job for which I&amp;rsquo;m applying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to &lt;strong&gt;add in all the things you want to do&lt;/strong&gt;, the project ideas, the skillsets you&amp;rsquo;d like to have, the places you&amp;rsquo;d like to go, the things you want to learn. This list has two purposes. First, it&amp;rsquo;ll help you identify some of the things you want to get out of a job (the ones related to job function, anyway &amp;ndash; for more on this, see the section below), which can help to determine whether or not you&amp;rsquo;re legitimately interested in the job for which you&amp;rsquo;re applying. Second, this list becomes the list of questions you ask at the end of the interview. You know, when the interviewer says, &amp;ldquo;Do you have any questions for us?&amp;rdquo; You should always have at least a few questions prepared, and those questions can come from this list of goals. (You should also make sure you have at least one question to ask that demonstrates how thoroughly you read the organization/company&amp;rsquo;s website; I usually ask about the methodology of a specific project, or to inquire about a recent change in the organization/company.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a life inventory not only helps you figure out where you&amp;rsquo;re at and what you want, but once you&amp;rsquo;ve created it, it makes applying for jobs so much easier.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Job Search&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now you&amp;rsquo;ve figured out where you&amp;rsquo;re at and where you want to go. How do you figure out what jobs to apply for? Even in geospatial, there are a multitude of options: GIS Technician, GIS Developer, Cartographer, GIS Databse Administrator, government, private sector, nonprofits&amp;hellip; the list goes on and on. &lt;a href=&quot;http://idealist.org&quot;&gt;Idealist&lt;/a&gt; has identified what it calls the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.idealist.org/info/Careers/SelfKnowledge/Lenses&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Five Lens Framework&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; for determining the frames through which individuals see their careers. That list is specifically geared toward nonprofit job seekers, so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t include what I think is an important part of many job searches: money. The framework (with my addendum) involves the following six lenses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organization: You want to work at Specific Company X. It is less important what you do there, so long as you are working there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Role: It is not so important which company you work at, so long as you get to do Job Duty Y.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System: You are flexible when it comes to job duty and company, so long as the company has Organiational Structure Z.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issue: You want to work solving Social or Technical Problem Q. Different types of organizational structures and job duties are less important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Population: You want to serve Population J. This can be humans, animals, the environment, whatever, but so long as through your job you are helping this population you care about, you&amp;rsquo;re content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compensation: You want to make a certain amount of money. (Sidenote: I know there&amp;rsquo;s stigma attached to this, but being adequately compensated for your life is something that is totally okay to desire and nothing to be ashamed of!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the exercise above, when you were taking a life inventory, one of the things you wrote down was a list of what you want to get out of a job. Take a look at this list and try to identify which of these categories your goals fit into. &lt;strong&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also okay to want more than one thing.&lt;/strong&gt; For me, it is a combination of role, system, and population: I want to conduct specific job tasks, I like certain types of organizations and work environments, and I care that my work is affecting a certain population. The spcific company I work for, the problems I&amp;rsquo;m solving, and my compensation are less important. Still important, but less so. Identifying which of these lenses is more prevalent for you can be extremely helpful in deciding which jobs to apply for, and if you get lucky enough to have to choose between multiple offers, your self-knowledge about these lenses will certainly come in handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information and advice about what to do once you&amp;rsquo;ve identified which lenses you value, see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.idealist.org/info/Careers/SelfKnowledge/Lenses&quot;&gt;Idealist page on the Five Lenses Framework.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Take A Deep Breath&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at you! Now you know all about yourself, and you&amp;rsquo;re starting to identify jobs that will give you what you want. I&amp;rsquo;ve often heard from people when I&amp;rsquo;ve given this advice, &amp;ldquo;But there are so few jobs in my field! Who am I to be picky when I&amp;rsquo;m just out of school?&amp;rdquo; It is true, we all need to make money to eat and drink beer and pay rent and so on. Ideally, this process doesn&amp;rsquo;t limit your job prospects, but actually helps you to &lt;strong&gt;realize the totality of your skillset&lt;/strong&gt; which can open the field a bit. I have seen many of my friends take the first job in the field that they were qualified for without considering what they really wanted, and most of them are now pretty sad to be in that situation. I have also seen friends take jobs that were seemingly out of their ideal career field that ended up being great investments: they learned a lot about what they enjoyed in a work environment, they learned new skills, they made new friends, and even if it didn&amp;rsquo;t work out in the end, they ended up learning a lot about themselves in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking stock is hard, but it helps you figure out who you are and what you want, which in turn can help in making decisions and generating a plan for moving forward. Take a deep breath: you&amp;rsquo;re on the right track, and you&amp;rsquo;re doing just fine.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Stay tuned for Part 2: Grabbing Onto It, which should be up next week. If you have any questions/comments/concerns, feel free to contact me via the link at the left.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Every Second</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/everysecond"/>
   <updated>2013-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/everysecond</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an email I just sent to my sister, Kimberly. I thought some of you might enjoy it as well. (Note: I may or may not have been inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://xkcd.com/1205/&quot;&gt;this xkcd comic&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Kim,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been doing some thinking about life, and time, and the things I want to accomplish, and the way I want to live my life. I came up with a new mantra for myself that I think will be helpful for you. This is how I communicated it to &lt;a href=&quot;http://bradsimantel.com&quot;&gt;Brad&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Every second is contributing to the sum total of seconds of your life. I want to be able to go through that list of seconds, were it to exist, pick one, and feel good about whatever I was doing during that second. In taking inventory of what that would mean, I made a small list of the things I&amp;rsquo;d like to spend my seconds on. Holding hands with you is pretty high up on that list, but also playing music, listening to music, dancing, biking, rowing, singing. Creating. Learning. Sleeping. These all count. Consuming information? Reading Twitter? Not so much. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s important to read and consume, but I want it to be in the context of creation. Of dreaming and teaching. Every second.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it might be a good exercise to constantly remind yourself of this, that your life is a conglomeration of seconds and what you do in each second is contributing to that sum total. What is the purpose of the activity you&amp;rsquo;re currently undertaking? Does it fulfill you? Is it helping you get where you need to go? Is it something you can&amp;rsquo;t avoid? Are you engaged and focused, or is your brain elsewhere? If so, where is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about your daily activities as contributing to the grand painting of your life may help to make some decisions and focus on the things that are important. For me, one of my challenges is talking about things and never actually doing them. So it is important for me to notice when I&amp;rsquo;m talking about something and when I&amp;rsquo;m actually doing it. I want to make sure I&amp;rsquo;m doing things more than talking about them. That I&amp;rsquo;m producing more than I&amp;rsquo;m consuming. Organizing my space, writing lists, getting ready&amp;hellip; this is all distraction from the goal. Create. Produce. Make. That&amp;rsquo;s how I grow. How do you grow? What feeds you? When are you in the flow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take some time to answer these questions for yourself. I bet you&amp;rsquo;ll be surprised and inspired by what you come up with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alyssa&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>If At First You Don't Succeed...</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/trytryagain"/>
   <updated>2013-04-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/trytryagain</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re talking a lot, but you&amp;rsquo;re not saying anything.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He didn&amp;rsquo;t mean to mimic David Byrne, but his exhausted, frustrated, post-argument comment could have just as easily been from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psycho_Killer&quot;&gt;Talking Heads 1977* classic&lt;/a&gt;. He could have just as easily been on stage in the big suit, limping around to new wave beats (or no-wave non-beats), full of vigor that would inspire a generation, and generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there was no stage, no lights, no big suit. He was laying in bed, half-asleep, irritated and exasperated and out of options. I had spend the last hour, like I&amp;rsquo;ve spent many hours as of late, beating up his girlfriend, calling her names, making her feel small and inadequate. He was sick of it. He wanted it to stop. I was hurting someone he loves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His girlfriend is me, and I have a lot of trouble keeping my head above water when it comes to my skills, my aspirations, and, ultimately, my options. I don&amp;rsquo;t ever feel like I have what it takes to succeed because of various talents I don&amp;rsquo;t possesses. Because I have an idea of what I want that is arbitrary and societal and fabricated, and it&amp;rsquo;s not who I am or what I&amp;rsquo;m good at, and that makes it hard for the brain to cope with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he did what he had to do. He did his best to get me out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In truth, he didn&amp;rsquo;t say the line &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; as written by Byrne and Frantz and Weymouth; he didn&amp;rsquo;t mean to make me the victim and him the killer. What he said was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;You talk about all these things, but you never actually &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; anything.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about this a lot last night as I laid awake for hours, pondering. It took me a while, but I realized that he was right. I don&amp;rsquo;t take the time, I don&amp;rsquo;t sit down and churn things out. I know that to get better you need to practice, so why don&amp;rsquo;t I practice? Why don&amp;rsquo;t I work? Why don&amp;rsquo;t I &lt;em&gt;try?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There it was. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; was the lightbulb. I don&amp;rsquo;t try! I&amp;rsquo;m so afraid of failure that I don&amp;rsquo;t even try in the first place. I dismiss options outright because of a fear that I will have an option taken away from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s the kicker, and something I am slowly realizing. The worst thing to happen if I try and fail is&amp;hellip; that I try something else. And if that doesn&amp;rsquo;t work? Try something else. It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt; that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I want to do, and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt; to have a ton of interests. And it&amp;rsquo;s even okay to be bad at things, and to still like them! But the more days that go by with me beating myself for not being a good cartographer and not having a good portfolio that I &lt;em&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; work on a map? That I &lt;em&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; try? I&amp;rsquo;m setting myself up for failure. I&amp;rsquo;m stacking the deck. I will always lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was 12 I started playing bass. I wanted to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim_Deal&quot;&gt;Kim Deal&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D%27arcy_Wretzky&quot;&gt;D&#39;arcy Wretzky&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim_Gordon&quot;&gt;Kim Gordon&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kathy_Foster&quot;&gt;Kathy Foster&lt;/a&gt;. And I wanted to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tina_Weymouth&quot;&gt;Tina Weymouth&lt;/a&gt;, too. Should I keep beating myself up for not being a bassist in a successful band? For not being &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aimee_Mann&quot;&gt;Aimee Mann&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esperanza_Spalding&quot;&gt;Esperanza Spalding&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kathi_Wilcox&quot;&gt;Kathi Wilcox&lt;/a&gt;?**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell no. I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep playing music, I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep making maps and writing Python scrapers and riding bikes and planning events. I&amp;rsquo;m Lyzi Diamond, and so long as I try, that can mean whatever I want it to mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*&amp;ldquo;Psycho Killer&amp;rdquo; was first performed in 1974 by the Talking Heads precursor The Artistic, then in 1975 by the Talking Heads, and finally recorded for the 1977 album, Talking Heads: 77. This note is in place specifically because I know my friends are the ones to nitpick. And that&amp;rsquo;s why I love them. :)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;**If you can name the bands that all of these women were in without clicking the links, you should email me, and we should be friends.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Circumlocution and Code</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/circumlocution"/>
   <updated>2013-04-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/circumlocution</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;¿Cómo se dice &amp;lsquo;roommate&amp;rsquo; en español?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve all experienced those moments when we can&amp;rsquo;t remember a word. It&amp;rsquo;s on the tips of our tongues, and we try, but we can&amp;rsquo;t seem to find it. Remarkably (or not-so-remarkably), this does not prevent us from communicating our idea. We just use other words to describe what we&amp;rsquo;re talking about, describing it instead of picking the exact word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I met this guy yesterday who had the most interesting job. He is a zoologist who focuses on birds!&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;You mean an ornithologist?&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Right, an ornithologist. Anyway, he had the cutest accent&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This practice is common in university language courses, where students are instructed to speak only in their language of study and not to utter a word of English. In these cases, where students do not have a command of the vocabulary in the new language, the conversations tend to consist of talking &lt;em&gt;around&lt;/em&gt; the actual words in order to foster meaning. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;¿Quién es ella?&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Ella vive en mi casa.&amp;rdquo;
[Translation: Who is she? She lives in my house.]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term for &amp;ldquo;roommate&amp;rdquo; in Spanish is &amp;ldquo;compañero de casa,&amp;rdquo; but &amp;ldquo;alquien que vive en mi casa&amp;rdquo; (someone who lives in my house) works just as well. The student in the example didn&amp;rsquo;t know the word for roommate, so he talked &lt;em&gt;around&lt;/em&gt; it. This is called &lt;strong&gt;circumlocution.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a newbie coder, I find myself frequently circumlocuting when writing code. My Python vocabulary is limited, but even with the small amount of knowledge I have obtained and the few methods I know, I can still effectively write scripts that execute without error. They&amp;rsquo;re not beautiful or concise, necessarily, but they &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;. As a beginner, this is extremely empowering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I have been writing a Python scraper to pull some data from an HTML page. (I&amp;rsquo;ll write a post dedicated to it with more specifics when it&amp;rsquo;s done.) A part of the data I&amp;rsquo;m trying to gather requires me to break apart a string into pieces and insert those pieces into separate columns. Using my limited Pythonic vocabulary and the help of an external library, I was able to isolate the string I needed to break apart&amp;hellip; but then I was stuck. Cursory Google searches instructed me to use regular expressions, but that required knowledge I didn&amp;rsquo;t have, and time I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to acquire said knowledge. Instead, I used a piece of vocabulary I already knew: Python&amp;rsquo;s built in partition() method. By selecting elements from resulting tuples and using partition() a few times, I finally got the pieces I wanted into my database. I talked &lt;em&gt;around&lt;/em&gt; the problem, circumlocuting using the vocabulary I knew to achieve my desired end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it worked. Just as &amp;ldquo;person who lives in my house&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;roommate&amp;rdquo; mean roughly the same thing when communicating with a peer, the partition() method and the result of a regular expression mean roughly the same thing to the computer. And it worked. And that felt &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will I continue using this roundabout method forever? Certainly not. But I bet knowing the long way around and writing too many lines of code will be helpful when I learn the shortcuts that are used by more proficient programmers to achieve the same ends. Not only will I understand what I&amp;rsquo;m doing better, I will have made the mistake myself and be more encouraged to try it another way in order to make progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vote that experienced developers encourage beginners to write code this way, to try the long way, to solve problems using the tools they have. Too often novice coders are afraid to show what they have created for fear of being belittled by those who know how to do it &amp;ldquo;better.&amp;rdquo; If we turn circumlocution into an accepted learning tool and begin to see it as part of the process, I believe that more beginners will feel confident showing the world their code and will later relish the opportunity to see where they&amp;rsquo;ve been and how far they&amp;rsquo;ve come.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Secret To Productivity? Forgiveness.</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/productivity-forgiveness"/>
   <updated>2013-04-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/productivity-forgiveness</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have often been given the advice, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t try to do everything. You will never succeed. Instead, try to do one or two things at a time, really well.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also been given the advice, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t succumb to fear of missing out. Whatever you&amp;rsquo;re imagining is probably ten times cooler than what&amp;rsquo;s actually going on.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But still, I find myself committing to everything and actually doing nothing because I don&amp;rsquo;t know what to prioritize. And it sucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, this website. I made it in two days when I was visiting the east coast during a horrendous cold snap this January. Since then there have been no blog posts, no maintenance. I have learned so much about HTML and CSS since then, and yet I haven&amp;rsquo;t put any of it into practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because I&amp;rsquo;m paralyzed. I have seventeen different things pulling my attention at any given moment, and it is impossible to focus on any one of them at a given time. There&amp;rsquo;s a little voice telling me in the back of my head that I should be doing something else, that something else is more important. So I don&amp;rsquo;t do anything at all, because I can&amp;rsquo;t decide what it is that I should do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the rare occasion that I can bring myself to do something, I am not actually thinking about whatever I&amp;rsquo;m doing; I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about all of the things I&amp;rsquo;m not doing and should be doing. Paralysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been introspecting and meditating on this for a while. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to figure out why it is that I feel so guilty all the time, why I feel like I need to do things in a specific order or I&amp;rsquo;m doing it wrong. The answer is convoluted, but ultimately I have found that I hold myself to an impossibly high standard. The need for order in a mind that is predisposed to chaos is another way that I can move the goalposts and never be satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of that, I have decided to set some simple goals for myself. The individual tasks are irrelevant, because they all center around the same thing: &lt;strong&gt;forgiveness&lt;/strong&gt;. I need to forgive myself. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve started forgiving myself, I have actually gotten things done. I&amp;rsquo;ve figured out the things I like to do and the things I&amp;rsquo;d rather not do (there&amp;rsquo;s always the stuff you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to do regardless of whether or not you want to, but that&amp;rsquo;s irrelevant here). And I have on the whole felt better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgiveness also means removing the &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; from my internal dialogue and focusing instead on the &amp;ldquo;want.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Forget what you &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt; do,&lt;/em&gt; I tell myself. &lt;em&gt;What do you &lt;strong&gt;want&lt;/strong&gt; to do?&lt;/em&gt; The answers didn&amp;rsquo;t surprise me, but the way I have felt after acting on them was certainly startling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is still hard for me. I am still trying to navigate using this new compass. But I&amp;rsquo;m hoping that with some work, dedication, and practice, it will lead me to places previously thought unreachable.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Fork, brook, run? A neat toponym visualization by a UO geographer.</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/fork-brook-run"/>
   <updated>2011-11-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/fork-brook-run</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.files.wordpress.com/2011/11/dwatkins_usstreamnames_big.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work a few weeks ago, we were having a conversation about how different areas of the country pronounce the word “creek.” There is the urban pronunciation, “creek,” and the rural pronunciation, “crick.” The argument was over whether or not these two bodies of water were actually geographically different or just indicative of cultural influence in pronunciation (dialect shift). Language is a funny thing, and linguistics is an interesting science, but none of us are linguists. We agreed to disagree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after, I stumbled upon this map by my former classmate and University of Oregon geography student Derek Watkins. Using the USGS National Hydrography Dataset, Derek symbolized bodies of water based on their toponyms, or generic place names. The patterns, as he points out in his &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.dwtkns.com/2011/generic-stream-terms/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; accompanying the map, are mostly well-explained, outlining historical trails, settlement patterns, and tendencies of weather:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Lite-Brite aesthetic notwithstanding, I like this map because it illustrates the range of cultural and environmental factors that affect how we label and interact with the world. Lime green bayous follow historical French settlement patterns along the Gulf Coast and up Louisiana streams. The distribution of the Dutch-derived term kill (dark blue) in New York echoes the colonial settlement of &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Nieuw_Nederland_and_Nya_Sverige.svg&quot;&gt;New Netherland&lt;/a&gt;&quot; (as well as furnishing half of a specific toponym to the Catskill Mountains). Similarly, the spanish-derived terms rio, arroyo, and cañada (orange hues) trace the &lt;a href=&quot;http://books.google.com/books?id=KOPdX2qaVrkC&amp;pg=PA66&quot;&gt;early&lt;/a&gt; advances of conquistadors into present-day northern New Mexico, an area that still retains some unique &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/2000/12/ferry.htm&quot;&gt;cultural&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://books.google.com/books?id=us_i7JfycYgC&amp;dq&quot;&gt;traits&lt;/a&gt;. Washes in the southwest reflect the intermittent rainfall of the region, while streams named swamps (desaturated green) along the Atlantic seaboard highlight where the coastal plain meets the Appalachian Piedmont at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fall_line&quot;&gt;fall&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#39;http://md.water.usgs.gov/publications/fs-157-00/html/location_big.gif&#39;&gt;line&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A quick aside on map design: The whole point of a map is to disseminate information. There is a tendency among amateur cartographers to want to make water blue, land green, and labels black. But if the information that the cartographer is seeking to convey requires further classification, it can be a benefit to the reader to make these elements, for lack of a better word, obvious. A visual hierarchy exists in the brain. We see things in a certain order depending on how they are displayed. It is for this reason that Derek chose a dark background with bright hydrological features because that is the part of the map he wished you to focus on. Cartography secrets revealed!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, the comments section actually addresses the “creek” vs. “crick” issue. Derek created the map using the Geographic Naming Information System (GNIS), a national standard for, yep, you guessed it, geographic naming. Did you know there’s a U.S. Board on Geographic Names? If you were ever a GIS intern, the answer is probably yes. Regardless, this map only displays the names as approved by this body, not the colloquial nomenclature, meaning that this map, although totally awesome, does not help me or my colleagues determine the answer to our question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In closing: are creeks and cricks the same thing? According to the United States government, yes. But as far as the cultural and regional lexicon? We may never know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXTRA CREDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; For the etymology of the word “creek,” check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=creek&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; from the Online Etymology Dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Scale Unimaginable: The Intersection of Art and Cart</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/scale-unimaginable"/>
   <updated>2011-11-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/scale-unimaginable</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lyzidiamond.files.wordpress.com/2011/11/monarchs.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;




&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An atlas never just shows you where you are, where you want to go to and how to get there. It also fires the imagination. Maps which chart rivers, mountains, towns, countries, far-away regions, oceans and continents can arouse intense feelings. An atlas combines reality and fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Maps evoke travel, exotic places and the allure of the unknown. Without a map, there would be no way to know precisely where you are. There is no ‘here’ without ‘there’. There is no world without a map.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;cite&gt;Louise van Swaaij and Jean Klare, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Atlas-Experience-Louise-van-Swaaji/dp/1582341001&quot;&gt;The Atlas of Experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most cartographers, myself included, measure the quality of our maps by the accuracy of data and analysis. The cleaner the line, the higher the product quality. But many map makers, information designers, and illustrators take a slightly different, more emotional approach to map design, incorporating the fantastical into the exact and the real into the imagined. One of the most notable is Rebecca Solint, and her cartographers Ben Pease and Shizue Seigel, in their 2010 book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ucpress.edu/book.php?isbn=9780520262508&quot;&gt;Infinite City: A San Francisco Atlas&lt;/a&gt;, published by the University of California Press. A catalogue of maps, culture, and history in one of the west coast’s most illustrious cities, the book seeks to teach the reader what’s beyond the page, the streets, the buildings, the lines and the water. Solint seeks to fold out a history on the page, using coordinates to tell a story. Her maps are snapshots in time, overlaying pieces of information that have sometimes clear but mostly tenuous connections, allowing the reader to discover historiographic relationships that would never have guessed existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional maps can also create an illusion of a static plane, while the world is in reality dynamic and multidimensional. Solint writes in her introduction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Places are leaky containers. They always refer beyond themselves, whether island or mainland, and can be imagined in various scales, from the drama of a back alley to transcontinental geopolitical forces and global climate. What we call places are stable locations with unstable converging forces that cannot be delineated either by fences on the ground or by boundaries in the imagination—or by the perimeter of the map. Something is always coming from elsewhere, whether it’s wind, water, immigrants, trade goods, or ideas. The local exists—an endemic species may evolve out of those circumstances, or the human equivalent—but it exists in relation, whether symbiotic with or sanctuary from the larger world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cartographic products as displayed by data analysts and statisticians can serve a variety of purposes. But we can sometimes forget to see the trees for the forest. Maps invoke emotions, regardless of their artistic content. Often, the inclusion of art and other creative cartographic elements can enhance those emotions and guide the reader to discover what was previously thought undiscoverable, or not previously thought of at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXTRA CREDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; For a bevy of nontraditional maps, check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.handmaps.org/&quot;&gt;Hand Drawn Map Association&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Maps Can Save Lives: A true story of GPS and the importance of navigation</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/maps-can-save-lives"/>
   <updated>2011-05-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/maps-can-save-lives</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Global positioning systems have ostensibly become the new atlases — most if not all new vehicles have internal GPS mapping devices, rendering old-school paper maps obsolete. But as drivers and navigators become more reliant on these devices, their safety may be put in severe danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the case for Alicia Sanchez and her six-year-old son Carlos, who ventured into Death Valley National Park in August of 2009, equipped with a GPS device and no paper maps to verify her surroundings. When the two traveled twenty miles into the park and got their vehicle stuck deep in sand, with little to no cell phone service available to call for help, Carlos passed away when their water supply dwindled and they did not receive assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another GPS user faced a similar dilemma when traveling in Glen Canyon National Recreation Area in Utah. After traveling 60 miles into the park, she hit Lake Powell — which had inconveniently not been documented in the GPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stories, as well as the stories of many other GPS-wielding travelers, are documented in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oregonlive.com/pacific-northwest-news/index.ssf/2011/05/missing_canadian_couple_experts_say_always_pair_gps_with_paper_map_realize_technology_not_infallible.html&quot;&gt;an Oregonian story from yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, with some advice on how to travel appropriately:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“Never ask the question, ‘What is the shortest route?’ if you are on a dirt road,’” said [Charlie] Callagan, a National Park Service wilderness coordinator in Death Valley, Calif.

The technology often trumps common sense for unwary visitors who put too much faith in the units that receive satellite signals at the speed of light. “It’s fancy, it’s the newest thing,” Callagan said. “How could it do me wrong?” [...]

Travelers should know that map data displayed by GPS units can be outdated, with roads that no longer exist. Callagan, for instance, said he has persuaded some manufacturers to remove dangerous road segments from their Death Valley databases.

Outdoor experts recommend always carrying several maps and plenty of water and food. They suggest taking four-wheel-drives with heavy-duty tires into the backcountry or even two spare tires.&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Having and knowing how to use a paper map will always be helpful to travelers, even in the age of ubiquitous technology. Whether it be operator or mechanical error, GPS devices (and the underlying systems/companies that operate them) are fallable, and being able to handle yourself around a paper map and a compass could end up saving your life.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>On Design</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/on-design"/>
   <updated>2010-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/on-design</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Cartography is fast becoming the most practical comparative basis for integrating and reducing the vast reaches of modern information. If the geographer seeks to define a domain in terms of space in order to discover regions, and if the historian seeks to define a domain in terms of space and time in order to discover civilizations, the cartographer can be said to use space in order to inform us about all conceivable domains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;cite&gt;Jacques Bertin, Semiology of Graphics&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Skilled Pedestrian</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/the-skilled-pedestrian"/>
   <updated>2010-11-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/the-skilled-pedestrian</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The pedestrian is a social being: he is also a transportation unit, and a marvelously complex and efficient one. He is self-contained, self-propelled, and moves forward with a field of vision about 100 degrees wide, further widening this with back-and-forth scanning movements to almost 180 degrees. He monitors a host of equations: two crossing patterns at left front, 290 feet a minute, three on the right, angle on the cars 30 degrees and closing, a pair abreast dead ahead, a traffic light starting to flash DON’T WALK. In fractions of a second he responds with course shifts, accelerations, and retards, and he signals to others that he is doing so. Think of the orders and computers it would take to match him! Transportation engineers are spending millions on developing automated people-mover systems. But the best, by far, is a person.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;cite&gt;William H. Whyte, City: Rediscovering the Center&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Field Thoughts</title>
   <link href="http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/field-thoughts"/>
   <updated>2010-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lyzidiamond.com/posts/field-thoughts</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Geography is the study of relations between society and the natural environment. Geography looks at how society shapes, alters, and increasingly transforms the natural environment, creating humanized forms from stretches of pristine nature, and then sedimenting layers of socialization one within the other, one on top of the other, until a complex natural-social landscape results. Geography also looks at how nature conditions society, in some original sense of creating the people and raw materials which social forces “work up” into culture, and in an ongoing sense of placing limits and offering material potentials for social processes like economic development. The “relation” between society and nature is thus an entire system, a complex of interrelations. What was once a causal relationship mainly in one direction (the formation of humanity during natural evolution) becomes an equally causal interrelationship in the reverse direction (social evolution alters the “natural” environment). In this way, human activity continually remakes its natural context — nature comes to be socially constructed, in the sense both of social and economic forces remaking landscapes, and of the intervention of ideas and discourses. Understanding this system of relations requires that geographers be sophisticated natural and social scientists, find ways of combining the two, know the methods and be excited by the insights of both aspects of knowledge. Thus, the synthetic core of geography is a study of nature-society interrelations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;cite&gt;Richard Peet, Modern Geographic Thought&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>